<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Ratul Minhaz</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Fall</title><link>/posts/the-fall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/the-fall/</guid><description>If you cup your hands on both of your ears, you will hear a swishing sound that almost feels increases every few seconds. You might say that is the sound of your blood pulsating in your body, recycling carbon dioxide and bringing in new oxygen every now and then.
To me is is the sound of wind passing by us, as we fall through the eternal void. It is a reminder of that inevitable crash we all have to face when this brief flight we have been in since our birth ends and we stop moving forever.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/</guid><description>Hi there My name is Radek and I&amp;rsquo;m the author of this theme. I made it to help you present your ideas easier.
We all know how hard is to start something on the web, especially these days. You need to prepare a bunch of stuff, configure them and when that’s done — create the content.
This theme is pretty basic and covers all of the essentials. All you have to do is start typing!</description></item><item><title>Setting up Ember CLI Sass</title><link>/posts/2017-01-27-setup-ember-cli-sass/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017-01-27-setup-ember-cli-sass/</guid><description>Trying to set up Sass with Ember can be quiet problematic if you are using a version manager for Node. For example I was using a version manager called &amp;lsquo;n&amp;rsquo; and could not integrate Sass in anyway with my Ember app. It all boiled down to my Ember installation not finding libraries needed to compile Sass. These two modules were the reason of the problem: node-gyp and node-sass.
After fiddling around for a while I found out the proper way to setup Sass with Ember.</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ১</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-1-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-1-bn/</guid><description>Introductory data analysis and visualization</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ২</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-2-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-2-bn/</guid><description>Introductory data analysis and visualization</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ৩</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-3-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-3-bn/</guid><description>Introductory data analysis and visualization</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ৪</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-4-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-4-bn/</guid><description>Introductory data analysis and visualization</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: An Intertwinement of Disciplines</title><link>/posts/2015-11-26-sentiment-analysis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 13:03:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-11-26-sentiment-analysis/</guid><description>How often do you get the urge to know what others think about you, that is, your actions and preferences? No matter what the number is, you are not alone. Humans as individuals, have always been interested in knowing the opinion of the people around them. Should I talk to her? Is it a good idea to buy that car? Who should I vote? These are only the simplest examples of opinion related questions that arise in our minds every single day.</description></item><item><title>Musings about friendship</title><link>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 00:46:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</guid><description>As I see it, you can make friends in only two ways: one is a emotional journey where all your personal firewalls break down and you almost know how the other person feels like. Another way is through gradually increasing appreciation for someone where at a point you actually know what your friend is thinking. Now hold a moment before saying that friendship can&amp;rsquo;t be this much black and white. It&amp;rsquo;s usually not and I am not claiming otherwise.</description></item><item><title>Confessions of an impatient coder</title><link>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:41:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</guid><description>I am a very impatient person, and my attention span is short. My mom used to say that when I was a kid, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep playing with one toy for more than five minutes. If any skill a programmer needs more than anything else, that is patience. Luckily I was patient enough to sit tight and think about my skills as a programmer. I did a small SWOT(Strength, Weakness, Opportunities and Threat) analysis.</description></item><item><title>If Gitignore does not ignore</title><link>/posts/2015-04-15-if-gitignore-does-not-ignore/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 11:03:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-04-15-if-gitignore-does-not-ignore/</guid><description>Sometimes after changing your .gitignore the new (un)ignored files don&amp;rsquo;t get get behind the scenes, as you would have expected. The reason behind this is you have already committed the files that you added to .gitignore and now git is tracking the files. Unless you delete them git will keep an eye on any changes on those files as it would do with any other. To get the new .gitignore rule registered with the repo you will have to manually remove tho file(s) from git&amp;rsquo;s cache.</description></item><item><title>Writing for myself</title><link>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 00:03:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</guid><description>It’s 1:49AM and I can’t sleep. It’s a very usual thing for me, I guess. I have developed this habit of staying up at night a few years ago. I don’t really remember how I got this habit, surely not from studying. I used to talk to people on Facebook and other sites, especially foreigners who live in places with 12 hours of time difference. After a while I realized I didn’t need more than 4 hours of sleep a day.</description></item></channel></rss>