<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Ratul Minhaz</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Fall</title><link>/posts/the-fall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/the-fall/</guid><description>If you cup your hands on both of your ears, you will hear a swishing sound that almost feels increases every few seconds. You might say that is the sound of your blood pulsating in your body, recycling carbon dioxide and bringing in new oxygen every now and then.
To me is is the sound of wind passing by us, as we fall through the eternal void. It is a reminder of that inevitable crash we all have to face when this brief flight we have been in since our birth ends and we stop moving forever.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/</guid><description>Hi there I am Ratul! I am a Berlin based Data Engineer who sometimes plays the ukulele and dabbles in writing. I am originally from Dhaka, the capital of Bangladesh and currently on a mission to see all around Europe.</description></item><item><title>Setting up Ember CLI Sass</title><link>/posts/2017-01-27-setup-ember-cli-sass/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017-01-27-setup-ember-cli-sass/</guid><description>Trying to set up Sass with Ember can be quiet problematic if you are using a version manager for Node. For example I was using a version manager called &amp;lsquo;n&amp;rsquo; and could not integrate Sass in anyway with my Ember app. It all boiled down to my Ember installation not finding libraries needed to compile Sass. These two modules were the reason of the problem: node-gyp and node-sass.
After fiddling around for a while I found out the proper way to setup Sass with Ember.</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ১</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-1-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-1-bn/</guid><description>নির্বাচনের সময়টায় সবার মাঝে সাড়া পড়ে যায় কাকে কে ভোট দিবে তা নিয়ে। আপনি হয়ত আপনার বন্ধু-বান্ধব আর পরিবারের সদস্যদের জিজ্ঞেস করেছেন মতামতের জন্য। মোটামুটি কাছের সবার কাছ থেকে মতামত নিয়ে মনে মনে একটা ধারণা তৈরী হয় আপনার: কে বেশি ভোট পেতে পারে, কেনই বা মানুষ তাকে ভোট দিতে বেশি আগ্রহী, কি কারণে হেরে যাওয়া দল কম ভোট পেলে ইত্যাদি। আপনি যদি কখনও এ কাজ বা এরকম মানুষের মতামত নিয়ে ধারণা তৈরী করার মত কিছু করে থাকেন, তাহলে বলা যায় আপনি ডেটা সাইন্স ব্যবহার করেছেন!</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ২</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-2-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-2-bn/</guid><description>আজকের যুগে শ্রেফ ইন্টার্নেটে কানেকশন থাকলেই অজস্ররকমের ডেটা হাতের নাগালে চলে আসে। ওয়েবসাইটগুলো প্রতিনিয়ত অন্যান্য ওয়েবসাইটের সাথে তথ্য নিয়ে কথা বলতে থাকে। হয়ত মানুষের ভাষায় হয় না সে কথাগুলো, হয় বিভিন্ন API বা Application Programming Interface এর মাধ্যমে। ফেসবুক, টুইটার, গুগল ইত্যাদির API ব্যবহার করে আমরা এখন হরেক রকমের তথ্য পেতে পারি।
এই টিউটোরিয়ালটি ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি সিরিজের দ্বিতীয় পর্ব। অন্যান্য পর্ব:1. [প্রস্তুতি]({{ site.url }}/datasci-intro-1-bn)2. [ডেটা সংগ্রহ]({{ site.url }}/datasci-intro-2-bn) (&amp;lt;&amp;ndash; আপনি এখন এখানে)3.</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ৩</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-3-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-3-bn/</guid><description>API দিয়ে অনায়াসে অনেক অনেক তথ্য সংগ্রহ করতে পারা যেমন অনেক কাজের একটা ব্যাপার কিন্তু তেমনি মাঝে মাঝে এত তথ্য নিয়ে বেসামাল অবস্থায় পড়তে হয়। দেখা যায় যে কোন তথ্য হয়ত আমরা যেমনভাবে চাই তেমন ভাবে নেই, যেমন এই প্রোজেক্টের ক্ষেত্রে আমাদের দরকার অ্যাকাউন্টের বয়স, কিন্তু আমরা পাচ্ছি অ্যাকাউন্ট তৈরীর তারিখ। তাই তথ্য সংগ্রহের পরের ধাপ হল তথ্য বিশ্লেষণ এবং পরিপাটি করা।
এই টিউটোরিয়ালটি ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি সিরিজের তৃতীয় পর্ব। অন্যান্য পর্ব:1.</description></item><item><title>ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি - ৪</title><link>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-4-bn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2016-06-30-datasci-intro-4-bn/</guid><description>কোন কিছু হ্রাস-বৃদ্ধির হার বোঝার জন্য সবচেয়ে সহজ উপায় হল গ্রাফ আঁকা। স্কুলে-জীবনে লাভ-ক্ষতি বোঝার জন্য আমরা যে গ্রাফ এঁকেছি, সেই একই গ্রাফ দিয়ে নির্বাচনে কার অগ্রগতি বেশি-কম তা বোঝা যায় সহজে। ডেটা সাইন্সের ভাষায় এভাবে গ্রাফের মাধ্যমে তথ্যকে চিত্ররুপে দেখানোকে বলা হয় ভিজুয়ালাইজেশন। পাইথনের কিছু চমৎকার লাইব্রেরী আছে ভিজুয়ালাইজেশনের জন্য, আমরা ব্যবহার করব Plotly.
এই টিউটোরিয়ালটি ডেটা সাইন্সে হাতে খড়ি সিরিজের তৃতীয় পর্ব। অন্যান্য পর্ব:1. [প্রস্তুতি]({{ site.url }}/datasci-intro-1-bn)2. [ডেটা সংগ্রহ]({{ site.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: An Intertwinement of Disciplines</title><link>/posts/2015-11-26-sentiment-analysis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 13:03:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-11-26-sentiment-analysis/</guid><description>How often do you get the urge to know what others think about you, that is, your actions and preferences? No matter what the number is, you are not alone. Humans as individuals, have always been interested in knowing the opinion of the people around them. Should I talk to her? Is it a good idea to buy that car? Who should I vote? These are only the simplest examples of opinion related questions that arise in our minds every single day.</description></item><item><title>Musings about friendship</title><link>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 00:46:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</guid><description>As I see it, you can make friends in only two ways: one is a emotional journey where all your personal firewalls break down and you almost know how the other person feels like. Another way is through gradually increasing appreciation for someone where at a point you actually know what your friend is thinking. Now hold a moment before saying that friendship can&amp;rsquo;t be this much black and white. It&amp;rsquo;s usually not and I am not claiming otherwise.</description></item><item><title>Confessions of an impatient coder</title><link>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:41:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</guid><description>I am a very impatient person, and my attention span is short. My mom used to say that when I was a kid, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep playing with one toy for more than five minutes. If any skill a programmer needs more than anything else, that is patience. Luckily I was patient enough to sit tight and think about my skills as a programmer. I did a small SWOT(Strength, Weakness, Opportunities and Threat) analysis.</description></item><item><title>If Gitignore does not ignore</title><link>/posts/2015-04-15-if-gitignore-does-not-ignore/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 11:03:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-04-15-if-gitignore-does-not-ignore/</guid><description>Sometimes after changing your .gitignore the new (un)ignored files don&amp;rsquo;t get get behind the scenes, as you would have expected. The reason behind this is you have already committed the files that you added to .gitignore and now git is tracking the files. Unless you delete them git will keep an eye on any changes on those files as it would do with any other. To get the new .gitignore rule registered with the repo you will have to manually remove tho file(s) from git&amp;rsquo;s cache.</description></item><item><title>Writing for myself</title><link>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 00:03:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</guid><description>It’s 1:49AM and I can’t sleep. It’s a very usual thing for me, I guess. I have developed this habit of staying up at night a few years ago. I don’t really remember how I got this habit, surely not from studying. I used to talk to people on Facebook and other sites, especially foreigners who live in places with 12 hours of time difference. After a while I realized I didn’t need more than 4 hours of sleep a day.</description></item></channel></rss>