<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rants on Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</title><link>/categories/rants/</link><description>Recent content in rants on Ratul.rants(about="xyz")</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Ratul Minhaz</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 00:46:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/rants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Musings about friendship</title><link>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 00:46:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-10-04-musings-about-friendship/</guid><description>As I see it, you can make friends in only two ways: one is a emotional journey where all your personal firewalls break down and you almost know how the other person feels like. Another way is through gradually increasing appreciation for someone where at a point you actually know what your friend is thinking. Now hold a moment before saying that friendship can&amp;rsquo;t be this much black and white. It&amp;rsquo;s usually not and I am not claiming otherwise.</description></item><item><title>Confessions of an impatient coder</title><link>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:41:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-09-14-confessions-as-a-programmer/</guid><description>I am a very impatient person, and my attention span is short. My mom used to say that when I was a kid, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep playing with one toy for more than five minutes. If any skill a programmer needs more than anything else, that is patience. Luckily I was patient enough to sit tight and think about my skills as a programmer. I did a small SWOT(Strength, Weakness, Opportunities and Threat) analysis.</description></item><item><title>Writing for myself</title><link>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 00:03:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2015-03-14-writing-for-myself/</guid><description>It’s 1:49AM and I can’t sleep. It’s a very usual thing for me, I guess. I have developed this habit of staying up at night a few years ago. I don’t really remember how I got this habit, surely not from studying. I used to talk to people on Facebook and other sites, especially foreigners who live in places with 12 hours of time difference. After a while I realized I didn’t need more than 4 hours of sleep a day.</description></item></channel></rss>